Guide to the Louis Weinstock Papers and Photographs WAG.013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Louis Weinstock Papers and Photographs
circa 1910-1994, bulk 1930-1980
1930-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weinstock, Louis, 1903-1994
Gould, Susan Weinstock
Weinstock, John
WAG.013
5.25 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversized flat box, and 2 oversized folders.
Louis Weinstock was born in Hungary in 1903 and emigrated to the United States in 1923. He settled in New York City and in 1925 joined the Painters' Union, Local 499. Weinstock became one of the leaders of the "Rank and File" movement in District Council 9 of the International Painters and Paperhangers. He fought for Social Security and initiated the drive for unemployment insurance. Weinstock also led the Rank-and-File painters caucus in a fight against corruption in the union, defeating the corrupt leadership of the infamous Lepke-Gurrah racketeer gang and getting elected to the office of Secretary-Treasurer. In 1951, he was charged with conspiring to violate the Smith Act while teaching a trade union class; he was found guilty and sentenced to three years in jail. Weinstock retired from the union in 1963 and died in 1994 from heart failure.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Louis Weinstock's children, Dr. John Weinstock and Susan Gould, in 1995. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1995.028, 1995.029 and NPA.1998.008.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Louis Weinstock was born in Hungary in 1903 and emigrated to the United States in 1923. He settled in New York City and in 1925 joined the Painters' Union, Local 499. Weinstock became one of the leaders of the "Rank and File" movement in District Council 9 of the International Painters and Paperhangers. In 1926 Louis married Rose, also from Hungary and an activist in the International Ladies Garment Workers Union. During the Depression, Weinstock fought for Social Security and initiated the drive for unemployment insurance even though the American Federation of Labor (AFL) leadership was opposed to such policies. Weinstock, with the help of Harry Bridges of the West Coast Longshoremen (ILWU) and Elmer Brown of the Typographers Union (ITU) headed a committee to rally support from 3,000 AFL local unions and ultimately forced the reversal of the position of William Green, then head of the AFL Executive Council who was opposed to such reforms. During the struggle for the unemployed, Weinstock participated in hunger marches and led delegations to city councils, state capitols, and was part of the National Hunger March to Washington, DC in the early 1930s.
Weinstock also led the Rank-and-File painters caucus in a fight against corruption in the union. Weinstock defeated the corrupt leadership of the infamous Lepke-Gurrah racketeer gang and was elected to the office of Secretary-Treasurer, the highest office in District Council 9. He was elected Secretary-Treasurer in 1926 and for 11 years he served as either Secretary-Treasurer or President of District Council 9. Under the renewed democratic leadership the union initiation fee was reduced from $75 to $5 which increased membership, especially amongst minority and immigrant groups, and particularly among African Americans and Puerto Ricans. Additional benefits followed: increases in wages, better safety conditions, and shorter working hours.
Weinstock participated in numerous activities for both social change and for the Rank and File movement in District Council 9. His activism included attending the founding convention of the World Federation of Trade Unions in 1945. He was a delegate to the first World Peace Congress, held in Paris in 1949. He continued to work throughout his life on the important issues facing international trade unions. In 1950 Weinstock became the secretary of a May Day parade planning committee. In 1953 the permit for the parade was canceled because the U.S. Subversive Activities Control Board declared that the group must register under the McCarran Act for operating a "Communist front" organization. At this point in Weinstock's life he was defending himself against three separate federal prosecutions: the May Day charge of perjury for allegedly lying about the name of the organizing committee, a Smith Act charge of teaching anti-American labor history, and a McCarran Act charge branding him as a Communist.
On June 20, 1951 agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation showed up to take Weinstock to jail. He was charged with conspiring to violate the Smith Act while teaching a course on trade unionism in 1950. The Justice Department argued that some issues being taught could be viewed as advocating a violent overthrow of the U.S. government. In 1953 Weinstock was found guilty and sentenced to three years in jail and $6,000 fine. He was released from prison in May 1957 and continued to pay off the $6,000 fine in monthly installments for the next 19 years. After his release from prison in 1957, he was reinstated into the District Council 9 and continued his trade as a house painter until a massive heart attack in 1963 forced him to retire. In the 1960s he served as a business manager for The Worker, a newspaper published by the Communist Party of the United States.
After retirement, Louis and Rose moved to Los Angeles where they remained active by working with the Los Angeles Committee for Trade Union Action and Democracy (TUAD) and also coordinated a Senior Citizens Organization. During the 1980s he was active with senior citizens' organizations and was a delegate to the World Conference on Aging, organized by the United Nations, held in Vienna, Austria. Louis Weinstock died on November 26, 1994 at the age of 91 from heart failure.
Sources:
Gersh, Adolph B., Occupational Hazards and the Painter. New York: New York District Council No. 9, B. of P. D. & P. of A., 1937.
Hall, Burton H., editor. Autocracy and Insurgency in Organized Labor. New Brunswick: Transaction Books, 1972.
Montgomery, John Flournoy. Hungary: The Unwilling Satellite. New York: The Devin-Adair Company, 1947.
The Struggle of the New York Painters for Human Conditions. New York: District Council 9, Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America, No Date.
Zausner, Philip. Unvarnished: The Autobiography of a Labor Leader. New York: Brotherhood Publishers, 1941.
Scope and Content Note
The papers and photographs of Louis Weinstock document his life from the 1920s to his death in 1994. The collection includes personal artifacts as well as an extensive amount of material from his involvement with the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers. The collection is organized into seven separate series: personal, correspondence, writings, subject files, resource materials, ancillary materials, and photographs.
Arrangement
Most files are arranged chronologically within each series.
Organized into 7 series:
I, Personal
II, Correspondence
III, Writings
IV, Subject Files
V, Resource Materials
VI, Ancillary Materials
VII, Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sam Winn Papers (WAG 203)
Carl Blum Papers (WAG 100)
Frank Schonfeld Papers (WAG 027)
Daniel French Papers (WAG 101)
Frank Schonfeld Papers (WAG 027)
Burton Hall Papers (WAG 087)
Collective bargaining -- United States.; Color photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Insurance, Unemployment.; Unemployed; Social security.; Korean War, 1950-1953 |x Protest movements.; Labor unions -- United States.; May Day (Labor holiday) -- United States -- History.; Hall, Gus; Billings, Warren K., 1893-1972; O'Dwyer, William, 1890-1964; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; World Peace Congress; Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1862-1951; National Hunger March; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Winn, Sam; Weinstock, Louis, 1903-1994; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; French, Daniel, 1908-; Weinstock, Rose; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985; Lindelof, Lawrence P.; Healy, Dorothy, 1914-1990; Quill, Mike, 1905-1966; Gould, Susan Weinstock; Weinstock, John
- Series I: Personal
  - Biographical file, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards and Invitations, 1942-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards (oversize), 1943 (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS003, Folder 1)
  - Rose Weinstock file (wife), 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Attorneys' Records: Sacher, Abt, Forer, & Rein, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Birthday Celebrations, 1973, 1983, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial Records/Receipts, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Causes & Issues, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorials, Obituaries, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Letters from Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (orphan), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Writings
  - Speeches, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Draft of Memoir, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes for Memoir, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Weinstock Memoirs Publishing Committee, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Margaret S. Mahler Institute, Grant for Memoir, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - C.P.U.S.A., 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Communist Party USA: "The Economic Crisis, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - C.P.U.S. A. articles, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - C.P.U.S.A., undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hunger March Materials-news clips, press releases, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hunger March-originals, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Hunger March to Washington-Analysis, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cincinnati Rank & File Conference-Proceedings, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Unemployed Organizer Newsletters, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - AF of L Trade Union Committee for Unemployment Insurance and Relief, 1932-1933, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Tom Mooney articles, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Workers Alliance of America, 1930-1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - American Labor Party, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - US Dept. of Labor-Painters Vacation Hearing, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Painters Vacation Hearing, Local 186 New Haven, Connecticut, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - May Day materials, 1950-1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Supreme Court Opinions-Smith Act, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Smith Act-Defense Committee, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Smith Act Support for Weinstock-Correspondence, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Smith Act Trial Report, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Smith Act-Court Proceedings, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Federal Correctional Institution-Danbury, Rand Connecticut, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence in Prison-Danbury, Connecticut, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Record of Smith Act Cases, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Receipts of Payment to the Dept. of Justice, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Smith Act Materials, 1951-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Court of Appeals Re: Smith Act, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Walter- McCarran Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - District Council #9, 1932-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Examination of DC #9's Accounts, Stuart Chase, CPA, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Local Union 499, Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, & Paperhangers, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - New York District Council, 1936, 1946, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - NYS Conference Buffalo, New York, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rank & File" Program, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Local Union 848, (Weinstock's Home Local), 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - CIO-PAC, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NC-PAC, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Union Insurance Policies, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lemkin v Weinstock, Rarback v Weinstock, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Expulsion from the Painters' Union, 1945-1950, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Local Union 442, Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, & Paperhangers, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - DC #9, Re: Dan French, 1978, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - IBPAT Pension Plan, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 4th District Western Conference of Painters & Tapers, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 26th General Convention Reporter, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - News Clips- Corruption DC #9, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Painters Local Union 913 v Monroe, etc., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - William Duva, Int.'l Rep-personal papers, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Social Security, Medicare, & Healthcare, 1980-1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Senior Citizens-materials, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Health Care Reform, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series V: Resource Materials
  - Articles and Journals, 1930-1955 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Corruption Sources, 1930-1991 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Committee Minutes, 1932, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Unemployment Sources, 1932-1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Flyers, 1933-1981 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - News and Opinion: NYC Building Trades, 1944, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - International Sources, 1945-1990 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Rank and File Painter, Painters' Rank and File, The Voice etc…, 1946-1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - UAW-CIO Report on Racketeering and Gangsteriism, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - NY Law Journal, Labor Union Expulsion of Communist Party Member, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Daily News, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 10th World Trade Union Congress, Havana, Cuba, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Retirement Sources, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Joe Hill News, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Issues of Boomerang, United Electrical Workers of Chicago, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Programme of Economic and Social Demands, WFTU-Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Fact Sheet on Senator McCarthy, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - MyersonNotes, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Myerson Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Myerson Notes-Cold War, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Myerson printed material- Research, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Myerson bibliography, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Myerson correspondence Re: Abt, 1977-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ACTWU Archives, 1986, 1987, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Myerson Contacts for Interviews, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Myerson Correspondence with Weinstock, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Orphan Documents, 1932-1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Articles/News Clips, Communist Pary, 1929-1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Press Releases, Hunger March & Work Sharing, 1931-1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clips and Newspaper Articles, Hunger March & Work Sharing, 1931-1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Articles on Painters, News Clips, & Press Releases, 1931-1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Articles on Racketeering, News Clips, & Press Releases, 1937-1947 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Articles on Hungary-News Clips, 1946-1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - News Clips/Articles, 1981-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - News Clips (Orphan), undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series VI: Ancillary Materials
  - Committee on Un-American Activities, House of Representatives, 80th Congress, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board, 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Legal Documents, US Court of Appeals, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Legal Documents, US Supreme Court, 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series VII: Photographs, 1920s-1980s; 1940-1949
  Scope and Content Note
  Three-hundred-twenty-six black and white prints and 59 color prints, including images of these individuals: Warren K. Billings, "Mother" Ella Reeve Bloor, Fidel Castro, Joseph R. Curran, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Hugo Gellert, Gus Hall, Dorothy Healy, Fiorello LaGuardia, William O'Dwyer, Mike Quill, and Paul Robeson. Notable subjects depicted include May Day parades in New York City, and demonstrations protesting against the Korean War. Photographers include Hungarian immigrant photographers John Albok and Gabriel Hackett, Alexander Archer, and one photograph credited to A.H. Greene of the Film and Photo League.
  - 1920s?, circa 1920-1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1930s?, circa 1930-1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1940s - Restaurant souvenir photographs, circa 1940-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1940s?, circa 1940-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1950s?, circa 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1960s?, circa 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1970s?, circa 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1980s?, circa 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Congress Syndical Mondial, Berlin, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1990s?, circa 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reference photocopies of photographs of Louis and Rose Weinstock in passports and labor union membership books, 1928-1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photocopies of unidentified photographs (possibly family, friends, and political colleagues), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photograph album (disassembled) of the Fot, Hungary orphanage, circa 1960-1970 (Box 5)
    General
    This item was presented to Louis Weinstock in memory of his visit to the orphanage on November 4, 1966. Captions are handwritten in Hungarian. Nineteen pages long (with photographs on both sides of the pages), it is arranged in original page order (indicated by an assigned page number written in pencil in square brackets on both sides of the pages). The album also includes a dedicatory note that accompanied the album, and a sample page of the original interleaving papers in the album has been retained.
  - Oversized photographs - panoramic, circa 1930-1950 (Box Tamiment Shared OS001, Folder 1)
  - Oversized photographs - miscellaneous, circa 1930-1950; 1959 (Box Tamiment Shared OS001, Folder 2)